I mean honestly if this doesn't blow
your mind do you even have a soul the
towers of Hanoi problem is a classic
recursive problem that can cause endless
amounts of frustration when I first
encountered this problem it took me
several days to come up with the
solution and quite honestly I didn't
feel like I understood the solution
until after teaching it to many of my
former students years later the setup of
the problem is as follows
you have three rods one of the rods has
some number of discs of varying sizes
placed on it with the largest discs at
the bottom and the smallest discs at the
top your goal is to move these discs one
at a time to a particular destination
rod in the same configuration as a start
before you get ahead of yourself and
declare this problem trivial there is
one important catch at any point in the
process of moving this you are not
allowed to move a larger disk on top of
a smaller disk this rule is what makes
this problem significantly more
challenging to solve in this video we
will dive into the towers of Hanoi
problem in three distinct phases first
we'll approach it from the perspective
of a puzzle where we'll try to come up
with a strategy for various
configurations then we'll transfer the
strategy into a recursive program to
solve this problem for any number of
disks in this section I'll also show you
some helpful tricks to solve challenging
recursive problems like this one and
lastly we'll deconstruct the recursion
to understand what's really going on
underneath the hood with some nifty
animations that I'm pretty sure you
won't want to miss so make sure you
stick to the end of the video all right
let's get started let's focus first on
three this since the solutions to the
one disc and to discern two interesting
for analysis purposes I highly recommend
pausing the video and taking a second on
your own to see if you can find the set
of moves to get these three disks to the
rightmost rod our goal is to come up
with a general strategy for solving this
problem if you're like me your first
go-to strategy and any type of puzzle is
random guessing and honestly there's no
shame in that random guessing is the
oldest strategy in the books so if I'm
looking at this problem the first thing
I might try is to move
smallest disk to the middle rod and then
the next move is basically forced from
there I would move the green disc to the
rightmost rod since I can't move it to
the second rod because that would
violate the rules after that the next
move that makes the most sense is to try
and move the smallest disk to the
rightmost rod and at this point after I
finished completely destroying the order
of this problem with three random moves
I think it might be a good idea to
evaluate what I've done so far well
unfortunately it's not looking too good
it looks like we are a little bit stuck
because what we really want is the
bottom disk below the disks that we
currently have on the third rod what we
just did by random guessing seems to be
pretty counterproductive to that point
so at this point in the problem I might
decide okay I might just want to start
over and reevaluate but from this random
guessing experience we've learned one
important fact we need to first think
about moving the largest disk from the
first rod to the destination rod and if
we take this idea one step further
before we can even think about doing
that we're going to have to deal with
the top two disks and we have to deal
with them in a careful manner so we can
eventually move the largest disk to the
destination rod this means our only
option is that we have to find some way
to move the top two disks to the second
rod okay so now that we split our
problem into more reasonable subtasks
let's solve them one by one to move the
top two disks to rod two we first move
the smallest this to Rod three after
which we move the middle disc to rod two
and finish up the subtasks by moving the
smallest disk to rot two and now we are
free to move the largest disk to Rod
three all right so what's next well from
here the solution is actually pretty
clear we need to move the top two disks
from the second rod to the third rod now
and to achieve this we move the smallest
disk from the second rod to the first
draw to get another way we then move the
middle disk from the second rod to third
rod followed by the the final step of
moving the smallest disk to the
destination rod and there you go we've
just solved towers of nine for three
disks
he was a quick recap of what we did we
first found a way to move the top two
disks a second rod allowing us to then
move this largest disk to the
destination rod and after this we
finished off by moving the top two disks
from the middle rod to the destination
run okay so now let's go one step
further and see if we can solve this for
the N equals four case by utilizing a
similar strategy to what we've just
developed before I go through the steps
to solve this take a second to pause the
video and see if you can come up with
the steps on your own applying the
general strategy to this new problem we
want to now move the top three disks
from rod 1 to rod two how do we do this
well one interesting thing about solving
this problem is that it's basically like
ignoring the largest disk even exists
and solving a general three disk towers
of Hanoi problem we're now our
destination is the middle rod make sure
you take a second to understand the
mapping that we just did and looking at
the simpler problem we know how to solve
it now right we basically solved the
version of it earlier to solve this sub
problem we move the top two disks a
third rod we achieve this by moving the
top distance second rod the middle disk
to the third rod and finished off by
moving the top disk from the second rod
to the third rod this now makes way for
the largest disk moving into the desired
position and now to finish off the sub
problem we once again move the top two
disks but this time from the third rod
to the second rod this sub task breaks
down into moving the top disk to the
first rod followed by moving the second
disk to the second rod and ending with
moving the top disk from rod 1 to rod to
notice the logic that we used here was
essentially the same as what we did
earlier and this is something that'll be
immensely important going forward in a
sense this is where the recursion of
this problem really originates going
back to the for this problem we now move
the largest disk from the first rod to
the destination rod
and now following our earlier strategy
we now move the top three disks from the
second rod to the destination rod and
the pattern once again shows up this is
essentially the same three this problem
we solved many times now we move the top
two disks from the middle rod to the
first rod and to do this we move the top
disk for the second rod to the third rod
we then move the second disk from rod
number two to rod number one and we
finish this sub task by moving the top
disk to the first rod we then move the
third disk from the second rod to the
destination rod and our final sub task
is to move the top two disks from rod 1
to rot 3 once again we know how to do
this
we move the first disc from rod 1 to rod
to move the second disk to the
destination rod and finish off the whole
problem by moving our top disk to the
destination rod and that's the sequence
of steps for towers of Hanoi with for
this I know that was a lot so let's do a
quick overview of what we just did we
first moved the top three disks from rod
1 to rod two this required a couple of
intermediate steps where we first moved
the top two disks from brought one to
rod three next we move the third disk to
the middle rod and then finish the sub
task by moving the top two disks from
the last rod to the middle rod we then
move the largest disk to the destination
rod and lastly we finished by moving the
top three disks from the middle rod to
the destination rod which had the same
set of sub tasks we've encountered
several times so now that we have a
fairly good understanding of a strategy
for this problem let's now dive into a
formal problem statement we want to
write a function Hanoi that takes three
inputs and start and end and outputs a
sequence of steps to move n disks from
the start rod to the end rod here's a
quick example of an input and output so
that we understand how this problem
statement works
if we pass in N equals three start is
equal to one and n is equal to three
what that means is our start rod is in
rod number one and we have three disks
on that start rod our n rod is rod
number three and that's where this need
to reach for simplicity let's assume
that the start and end will always be
between one and three and that they will
never be equal to each other
let's also assume that n will always be
a positive integer so we won't have to
handle any weird edge cases for this
particular input the sequence of steps
that this function will output will look
like the following we've already gone
over how these steps are generated from
my strategy but here's a quick overview
of how the steps correspond to actual
movements of disks the basic
interpretation is that a pointing to B
means that we're going to move the top
disc from Brod a to rod B okay so how do
we get started on solving this problem
when I'm looking at any sort of
challenging problem I try to find the
easiest thing I can do to help me solve
the problem personally I've noticed that
there's definitely an intimidation
factor in tough problems like this and
knocking out something easy can help you
get over that initial intimidation one
of the easiest things we can do here is
to find a helper function that simply
prints a move in the appropriate format
defining this function is fairly
straightforward to do and looks like the
following so now that we got that either
way let's shift our focus over to the
main task we need to find a way to
programmatically generate a sequence of
steps for n disks we've already seen
many clues in our investigation that
point to the fact that we'll have to
solve this problem recursively but how
in the world can we come up with
something that works this is by no means
an easy problem and before we get into
that solution I want to take a quick
aside to go over an incredibly important
concept when solving recursive problems
whenever you have faced with a
challenging recursive problem there are
three key steps that you should follow
to make your life exponentially easier
these three tips have helped me
throughout my years of learning computer
science and save me a lot of pain the
first step when solving a general
recursive function f of n is to design a
solution that works
for F called on the input one this is
often referred to as your base case the
second step is the one that's the
hardest to accept but what we are going
to do is we're going to just go out on a
limb and assume that F called
on the input n minus 1 will work the
second step is often referred to as a
recursive leap of faith once we've made
this assumption we will then show how we
can define F called on n in a working
manner using the function calls to F on
n minus 1 here is some intuition for why
these 3 steps work think about solving
this recursive problem F of n as trying
to knock down n dominoes where you only
get to knock down the first domino you
want to show that the ant domina will
eventually be knocked down how do you do
this well you know that if you just have
one Domino it's obviously going to work
out because you can just knock it down
this is an analogy to step one from here
what you can do is just assume at some
point the N minus 1
Domino will eventually fall this is the
analogy to step 2 and now to guarantee
the ant Domino will fall we have to put
this download just close enough to the N
minus 1
Domino so that when that domino falls
the nth Domino what respectively fall
this is the analogy to step 3 and once
we do that all the dominoes fall I want
to emphasize here that all three steps
are equally necessary for this to work
out if we don't get the base case right
that means the first domino never falls
if we don't make the assumption that F
called on and minus 1 works that's
similar to the situation where the N
minus 1
Domino never actually falls in which
case there's no way that the nth Domino
is gonna fall and lastly if we don't
properly define the relationship between
F of N and F of n minus 1 that's
basically like putting the nth Domino
too far away from the N minus 1
Domino so in that case the n Domino also
never falls
it's by moving the Domino close enough
to the N minus 1 Domino that the nth
domino falls
so let's now apply these three steps to
solving towers of Noi starting with step
one we want to show how we appropriately
handle the base case for this problem
when n is equal to one that's easy
enough since if we only have one disk
all we have to do is move that one disk
from the start to the end in our problem
statement this is equivalent to calling
print move with the arguments start and
end that takes care of step 1 now let's
move to step 2 in the process of solving
towers of Hanoi for any N what it means
to assume the F of n minus 1 works is
that we can just accept that any version
of towers of Hanoi call an N minus 1
will work it's important to remember
that this includes a variety of starting
and ending positions and we're just
going to assume that all of these
subproblems work now with that
assumption that any call to towers of
Hanoi on n minus 1 works let's move to
the third step where we need to show how
we can solve and disk towers of Hanoi
problems using the solutions to towers
of Hanoi called on n minus 1 there's one
minor issue though the first thing we
need to take care of is we currently
have a reference to the start and end
rod but we somehow need to have a
reference to the other rod in the
process one quick and easy way to do
this is by utilizing the rod numbers
since the first second and third rods
are labeled 1 2 & 3 respectively the
other rod will always be 6 minus the sum
of the start and end rods and now that
we have the other rod we can now execute
the first step of the strategy that we
developed earlier we want to first move
the top n minus one disks from the start
to the other the neat thing about the
framework that we've defined for solving
this problem is that the first step is
exactly equivalent to solving the
following towers of Hanoi problem on n
minus one disks by the second step of
recursive problem solving we can assume
this call works so we can use it as part
of our solution this corresponds to the
recursive call to annoy called on n
minus 1 start and other once we've
completed a step we can then proceed to
moving the last disk from the start to
the end this corresponds to a call to
pray
move with the arguments start and end
and now the final step is to move the
top n minus one disks from the middle
rod to the destination rod this
subproblem is essentially the same as
solving Hanoi for n minus 1 disk but a
start disk is the middle and the end
disk is the last disk this means we can
assume that the sub-problem works as per
our framework and the corresponding
recursive call is Hanoi with the
arguments n minus 1 other and end and
following these steps successfully
solves towers of Hanoi for n disk and
this does indeed end up being a valid
recursive solution now before we move on
I want you to take a second and look at
the final logic and really take a moment
to appreciate it I mean how crazy is it
that such a seemingly tricky problem
ends up having such a simple solution I
remember when I first solved this
problem my mind was absolutely blown
away I mean honestly if this doesn't
blow your mind do you even have a soul
this is really an amazing example of the
power and beauty of recursive problem
solving and for completeness he is a
fully developed solution to this problem
in Python the nice thing about going
through all this work is that the code
basically writes itself
now at this point some of you might be
looking at the solution and think okay I
understand how it works within the
recursive leap of faith' framework but
how does the actual recursion work fear
not let's answer that question I think
the best example to take a deep dive
into is the one we started off with
annoying with three disks where we want
to move the three disks from the first
rod to the third rod the first recursive
call
we'll call Hanoi on two disks with the
start rod as Rod one and the end rod as
rod two here's what that represents this
recursive call forces us to go back into
the function where we now get another
recursive call to Hanoi this time on one
disk where we want the single disk to
move from one to three here's a visual
example of what this call is trying to
achieve and this recursive call will go
back into the function where we actually
hit up base case which then prints the
move from rod 1 to rod 3 and this is a
very first move in the towers of Hanoi
problem visually what this represents is
that all our recursive calls before had
changed state because we now have
officially made our first move
after making a first move we have
officially completed the recursive call
to Hanoi on one disk which now means we
have to complete the recursive call to
Hanoi on two disks this means we now
have to call print move on rods one to
two which has the following effect this
is the second move in this particular
towers of our problem after completely
in the second move we still have to
finish computing the recursive call to
Hanoi on two disks which now makes its
final recursive call on a single disk
from rod 3 to rod 2 which has the
following visual representation this
hits the base case once again where we
now make the third move which is to move
the disk from rod 3 to rod two here's
the effect of that on the overall
problem
and this now completes our first
original recursive call which was step
one in our earlier strategy of moving
the top two disks from the first rod to
the second rod what's next is step two
of that strategy where we move the last
rod from rod one to the destination rod
that's a simple print call which has the
following effect that actually ends up
being the fourth move in the sequence
this now leads us to the final step
which involves moving the top two disks
from the second rod to the destination
rod that kicks off the following
recursive call this kicks off a similar
sequence of events the second recursive
call goes back into the function where
we now make a recursive call with one
disk moving from the second rod to the
first rod this it's the base case where
we now print this move which is where
the fifth move in the sequence comes
from here's the effect of that on the
overall problem
[Music]
the sixth move then follows by now
moving the disc from the middle rod to
the destination rod here's the effect of
that on the overall problem
and finally the seventh and final step
involves the final recursive call on one
disk moving from the first rod to the
third rod which once again hits the base
case that actually prints out the last
move
[Music]
and there you have it that's how the
towers of paranoid recursion unravels
it's really quite amazing how it all
works out especially if it's your first
time seeing it so I highly encourage
working through some examples on your
own to convince yourself that things do
indeed work out as they are supposed to
before I conclude this video here's a
big-picture recap of how we went about
solving towers of Hanoi we first took a
step back didn't even think about the
code recursion algorithms or anything
and just trying to understand how we as
someone trying to solve a puzzle might
go about solving this problem this is
something I really encourage doing when
you encounter a tough problem don't be
afraid to take a step back and take a
look at things from a different
perspective following this we developed
a strategy and use a strategy to
implement our occurr civ solution on the
way here we learn about the recursive
leap of faith and how it can help us
simplify particularly challenging
problems and lastly we took a step
deeper into the problem to understand
how this recursion works out
[Music]
thanks for watching me and as always I'd
appreciate it if you hit the like button
if you enjoyed it if you want to see
more content like this be sure to hit
the subscribe button and if you want to
more directly support this channel be
sure to check out the patreon page
linked in the description below see you
in the next video